{"tossups": [{"question": "Description acceptable The \u201cBlack Nobility\u201d, nicknamed for their mourning of this action, were families rendered largely powerless by it. Legislation passed a year after this action, which was not accepted by the leader that it gave special diplomatic privileges, was called the Law of Guarantees. While marching to attempt this action, an army of volunteers was defeated after their commander told them not to fire back during the brief standoff at the Battle of (*) Aspromonte. After the Expedition of the Thousand, Garibaldi was wounded in battle while leading an army to perform this action, with a slogan that promised to accomplish it \u201cor death\u201d. After the deposition of Napoleon III and the removal of the French garrison which previously prevented it, this action made a \u201cprisoner\u201d out of Pius IX in 1870. For 10 points, identify this military action, the final phase of Italian unification that created issues resolved by the Lateran Treaty", "answer": "the Italian capture of Rome from the Papal States (accept answers indicating the use of force to obtain control over Rome; prompt on answers involving Italian unification by asking \u201cwhat part\u201d)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "American adventurer Josiah Harlan wrote that an exiled former ruler of this empire was immensely cruel to his servants, including a time when the wind blew down his tent during a picnic, for which he castrated the slave who put it up. The rulers of this empire adopted a title meaning \u201cpearl of pearls\u201d. In response to the forces of this empire destroying the Golden Temple, (*) Baba Deep Singh led a Sikh militia to Amritsar, apocryphally continuing to fight after being decapitated while holding his head in his hand. This empire briefly established itself as the preeminent power of northwest South Asia following its victory over the Maratha Confederacy at the Third Battle of Panipat. For 10 points, what is this empire that ruled most of modern Afghanistan and Pakistan in the late 18th and early 19th centuries?", "answer": "Durrani Empire (accept Sadozai Kingdom)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "During an 1894 outbreak of bubonic plague, this man\u2019s spirit supposedly revealed through a planchette that he was in charge of the Department of Epidemics in heaven. The ghost of this man apocryphally appeared to a Buddhist monk asking for his head, only for the monk to ask about the heads of those this man had slain, convincing the ghost to become a Buddhist protector of the faith. A statue of this man has typically overseen rituals performed by the triads of southern China. One account claims that after capturing this man, P\u0101n Zh\u0101ng took his weapon, the (*) Green Dragon Crescent, which was later reclaimed by this man\u2019s son. A novel by Lu\u00f3 Gu\u00e0nzh\u014dng claims that this man swore the Peach Garden Oath with his sworn brothers Zh\u0101ng F\u0113i and Li\u00fa B\u00e8i. For 10 points, name this heavily mythologized, real-life general of the Three Kingdoms period who was later deified as a god of war.", "answer": "Gu\u0101n Y\u01d4 (accept Gu\u0101n D\u00ec, Gu\u0101n G\u014dng, Gu\u0101n Sh\u00e8ng D\u00ec J\u016bn, Gu\u0101n \u00c8r Y\u00e9, Y\u00fanch\u00e1ng, or Marquis Zhu\u00e0ngm\u00f3u)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "During the Fatimid rule of this region, artificial reservoirs called jabiya were built during a sort of \u201cgreen revolution\u201d that led to a period of substantial export of wheat across the Mediterranean. A ruler of this region deported thousands of Muslims to the city of Lucera, where they would live until its sack by Charles II. During a period of rapid urban expansion, rulers of this region built the Al-Khalesa suburb in the city of Bal\u2019Harm.\u00a0 The cultivation of citrus fruits, sugar cane, and dates began in this [emphasize] non-Iberian region during the (*) Kalbid dynasty, which collapsed into its own fractious taifa period. Aghlabid soldiers sailed north and defeated Byzantine forces during this region\u2019s long period of Muslim conquest, which was reversed by rulers of the Hauteville dynasty established in a nearby peninsula. For 10 points, name this island region, where Muslims ruled over Jews, Greeks, and Catholics until supplanted by the Normans under Roger Bosso and Robert Guiscard, who founded a namesake medieval kingdom.", "answer": "Sicily", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable Newspaper articles like \u201cA Disgusting Spectacle\u201d by The Oregonian chronicled Helen Emery\u2019s attempts to evade these laws. The history of these laws are chronicled in Peggy Pascoe\u2019s book What Comes Naturally. A court case involving these laws concerned a move to Washington, D. C. to avoid a 1924 \u201cIntegrity Act\u201d. These laws were partially overturned by McLaughlin v. Florida, and over eighty years earlier they had been upheld by (*) Pace v. Alabama. Seaborn Roddenbery proposed a nationwide one of these laws that used the \u201cone-drop rule\u201d. These laws were struck down by a 1967 court case that was cited as a precedent for Obergefell v. Hodges. For 10 points, name this type of law that was the subject of Loving v. Virginia.\u00a0", "answer": "Anti-Miscegenation Laws (accept any answer that describes laws that prohibit interracial marriage or relationships; prompt on \u201cJim Crow laws\u201d)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A later culture lamented the departure of a likely mythical king of this culture by evoking the abandoned \u201cserpent house\u201d, \u201cturquoise house\u201d, and \u201chouse of beams\u201d in its capital. That same later culture contrasted the high culture of the inhabitants of this culture with the \u201cbarbarism\u201d of the Chichimecs. Jorge Acosta excavated several \u201cAtlantean figures\u201d in this culture\u2019s capital and interpreted them as the supports for the superstructure of its Pyramid B. Pulque (\u201cPOOL\u201d-kay) was legendarily invented by a woman named Xochitl (\u201cSHOW\u201d-cheetle) and presented to Tecpancaltzin, a ruler of this culture. It\u2019s not (*) Teotihuacan, but the Mexica (\u201cmay-SHE\u201d-kah) passed through the ruins of this culture\u2019s capital on their way to settling the Valley of Mexico, which inspired the layout of Tenochtitlan and other Aztec cities. For 10 points, name this Pre-Columbian culture of central Mexico, whose capital was Tula.", "answer": "Toltec culture", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The first legal guarantee of religious freedom was signed by a ruler of this region in the Treaty of Torda. After a peasant revolt caused by a bishop of this region demanding several years of tithes at once, three different ethnic groups in this region signed the Unio Trium Nationum; that political agreement established three ruling estates that excluded an ethnicity from the east. The Treaty of Speyer established a semi-independent Protestant principality in this region, which (*) John Zapolya ruled before contesting the royal claims of Archduke Ferdinand. The Szekelys [say-kays] and Saxons were two ethnic groups who held political power in this region, while the growing population of Vlach speakers were unrepresented. Along with Banat and Bessarabia, this region joined Moesia and Moldavia as part of a growing country previously ruled by Carol I after he joined the Entente side of World War I. For 10 points, identify this region ceded from Hungary to Romania in the Treaty of Trianon.", "answer": "Transylvania", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One emperor from this region had a right-hand man named Illus whom his empress Ariadne tried to assassinate. That emperor from this region faced the revolt of Basiliscus and proclaimed the Henotikon in an attempt to reconcile with the Monophysites. An imperial secretary and a tax-collector, Anastasius II and Theodosius III, were proclaimed emperor in turn by troops from this region, and the usurper Artabasdos was commander of the Opsikion province in this region. At its formation, most of the land covered by the (*) Theme defensive system was in this region, and it contained a sub-region that gave its name to a dynasty that ended the Twenty Years\u2019 Anarchy and began the policy of Iconoclasm, Isauria. Both this region and Armenia began to be conquered by the Seljuk dynasty after a battle in which Alp Arslan defeated Romanos IV, the Battle of Manzikert. For 10 points, name this region, which makes up most of modern-day Turkey.\u00a0", "answer": "Anatolia (accept geographical equivalents such as the Anatolian Plateau; accept Asia Minor before mention; accept Isauria before mention; accept Opsikion Theme before mention)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Though he only stayed there for eight days in 1897, a facility in Chennai originally built to store this resource has since become a museum to Swami Vivekananda. A cartoon in Puck shows Robert Van Wyck being saved from drowning by Tammany Hall in the backlash against his facilitation of Charles W. Morse\u2019s monopoly over this resource in New York City. Nathaniel Wyeth created a horse-drawn saw to cut this resource while in the employ of the first person to sell this resource commercially, its namesake \u201cKing\u201d, (*) Frederic Tudor. This resource was combined with sawdust or wood pulp to form pykrete. The use of this resource in railcars allowed Gustavus Swift to ship meat both across the country and internationally. For 10 points, name this resource harvested from frozen waterways for the preservation of food and the cooling of drinks.", "answer": "ice", "category": "History"}, {"question": "When Carthage laid siege to Saguntum in the lead-up to the Second Punic War, both Roman consuls were busy fighting these peoples, which may have delayed a response. In Natural History, Pliny the Elder uses the phrase \u201cproperly so-called\u201d when describing these people in a narrow definition. Despite originating in Greece in the eighth century BCE, a type of helmet named for these people with two ridges on the crown and elongated or triangular cheekpieces. The Laebaten kings ruled these people, whose last king (*) Gentius named one of the subdivisions of their new nakesake Roman province, which was west of the possibly related Dardani and south of Pannonia. Rome fought a series of wars beginning in the 3rd century BC with these peoples, led by Agron and Teuta, because their piracy threatened the eastern coasts of Italy. For 10 points, identify these barbarian peoples who occupied the coast of the Adriatic Sea in modern-day Croatia and Serbia.", "answer": "Illyrians", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A theme park based on the work of this author is currently in development in Blackpool, Lancashire. This author admitted to using \u201ctheatrical effects\u201d when his interpretation of the Cueva de los Tayos was challenged. The foreword of a book by Ronald Story hopes for the use of this author\u2019s work in high school and college logic classes as a model of sloppy thinking; that foreword was written by Carl Sagan. In one work by this author, a supposed description of a (*) vehicle similar to an \u201camphibious helicopter\u201d is the basis for a reinterpretation of a passage from the Book of Ezekiel. This author\u2019s most famous work claims that the lid of Pakal the Great\u2019s sarcophagus and the Nazca Lines are evidence for ancient people\u2019s contacts with aliens. For 10 points, name this Swiss pseudoscientist and author of Chariots of the Gods?", "answer": "Erich von D\u00e4niken", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Ibn Battuta described a group of cannibals known for producing this commodity, who refused to eat a larcenous scholar because he was \u201cwhite\u201d, meaning that he was not \u201cripe\u201d. It\u2019s not bekhen, but a source of this commodity is depicted on the Turin Papyrus Map. Portuguese interest in the east coast of Africa was largely due to the role the city of Sofala played in this commodity\u2019s trade in the region. This commodity was brought to widespread European attention by al-\u2019Umari in his description of the (*) Bambuk and Bure (\u201cboo-ray\u201d) regions of one kingdom. European traders believed that the Biblical land of Ophir lay in the hands of the Mwene Mutapa because of their trade in this commodity. The salt produced at Taghaza was mainly traded for this commodity. For 10 points, name this commodity, which Mansa Musa used to tank the economy of Egypt during his hajj.", "answer": "gold", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The tribe that names this kingdom was only pacified by King Wamba centuries after their neighbours had surrendered. A bishop named Lucas wrote about how a series of \u201clazy\u201d rulers of this kingdom began sending yearly tributes of maidens to pacify neighbouring enemies. A monk living in this kingdom created an unusually eastward-facing map for his large book called Commentary on the Apocalypse; that monk, Beatus, also participated in theological debates against the prevalent (*) adoptionist belief started by a man from south of this kingdom. This kingdom ended when its ruler moved out of its last capital at Oviedo in the Cantabrian Mountains. The bones of St. James the Great were found in a region under the rule of this kingdom, which was founded by a Visigothic nobleman after the Battle of Covadonga. For 10 points, identify this kingdom founded by Pelagius that Galicia, Leon, and Castille would develop out of, the first Christian kingdom during the Reconquista.", "answer": "Kingdom of Asturias", "category": "History"}, {"question": "These animals were ritually bled by the Tahltan people using either wolf or lynx bones before being carried in bags to be released in the forest. The DNA of a single one of these animals of a long-extinct subspecies survives in a venereally-transmitted cancer called CTVT. Due to the rarity of mountain goat hair, the Salish people selectively bred these animals to produce longer hair, which was used to produce sought-after blankets. A 2018 study traced the North American population of these animals to four separate migration events, the second one facilitated by the (*) Thule culture. The Aztecs raised a variety of these animals, sometimes as food, called xoloitzcuintli (\u201cshow-low-eats-QUEEN\u201d-tlee), named for their association with Xolotl (\u201cSHOW\u201d-loatle). That animal is also known as the Mexican Hairless. For 10 points, name these animals, whose most famous native American breed is the chihuahua.", "answer": "dogs (accept Canis familiaris or any other common name for dogs; do not accept or prompt on \u201cwolves\u201d)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A martyr of this denomination was supposedly romantically pursued by Diocletian before fleeing Rome, only to be romantically pursued by another ruler who killed her for refusing his advances before converting to this denomination. For his work translating Greek philosophy, David the Invincible is among the Holy Translators revered by this denomination. A king apocryphally cursed to behave like a wild boar was cured of his madness upon releasing the founder of this denomination from imprisonment at (*) Khor Virap. Apocryphally built on the site where the founder of this denomination saw Jesus descend from heaven and strike the ground with a golden hammer, Etchmiadzin (\u201cetch\u201d-myah-TSEEN) Cathedral is the mother church of this denomination. For 10 points, identify this Orthodox denomination founded by Gregory the Illuminator, the world\u2019s oldest national church.", "answer": "Armenian Orthodox Church (accept Gregorian Church before \u201cGregory\u201d)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The financial backers of this settlement were inspired to do so by the reports of two Native American men who had been kidnapped from their homeland of Mawooshin by George Waymouth. A plan map of this settlement was found in the Spanish General Archives in 1888 after having been sent to the country by Pedro de Zu\u00f1iga. The ship Gift of God departed with half of the settlers a mere four months after arriving at this settlement. The death of his older brother and subsequent inheritance of Compton Castle led second-in-command Raleigh (*) Gilbert to leave this settlement. The Virginia \u0327 likely the first European ship built in the Americas, brought the population of this settlement on the Kennebec River back to England. For 10 points, identify this settlement, which lasted only about a year after its 1607 founding as a ship-building center in modern Maine.", "answer": "Popham Colony (accept Sagadahoc Colony)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Persian chronicles contend that after being overthrown by, and forced to marry, Shah Mir, a queen of this region\u2019s Lohara Dynasty disemboweled herself and offered her intestines as a wedding gift to her new husband. A ruler of a kingdom in this region, Lalitaditya Muktapida, is claimed to have earned 100 wishes from the gods for feeding a starving brahmin in a past life according to a history by Kalhana. After paying the British 7.5 million rupees, Gulab Singh established the Dogra Dynasty in this region after the fall of the (*) Sikh Empire. The Poonch Rebellion preceded the signing of this region\u2019s Instrument of Accession by Hari Singh. Operation Meghdoot began a series of conflicts in this region over the Siachen Glacier. For 10 points, name this mountainous region of South Asia contested between India and Pakistan.", "answer": "Kashmir (accept Jammu and Kashmir)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In a book about these places in Britain, Indiana professor Norman J.G. Pounds argues that they were chiefly used for storing files. An account of one of these places describes pipes that would throw flour and a talking mechanical owl as two \u201cmachines of amusement\u201d, which was built by Robert II of Artois to pull practical jokes on people. In German-speaking areas of Europe, these places were often centered on structures called bergfried. They\u2019re not great houses, but rooms dedicated to the owners of these places were called (*) \u201csolar rooms\u201d. James of St. George was a prolific architect who designed many of these places built in the 13th century. Early examples of these places, which were built quickly on raised earthworks called mottes, were built extensively on England\u2019s western border after the Norman Conquest. For 10 points, identify these places, defensive stone structures built extensively by English kings to control Wales.", "answer": "castles (accept types of castles like motte and bailey; accept keep; don\u2019t accept or prompt on \u201chill fort\u201d)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Water flowed out of the title object and down the robe of a statue known as \u201cThe Goddess with a Vase\u201d found in this city. Terqa became the capital of the Khana Kingdom after the fall of this city. A bearded man and the goddess Lama accompany Ishtar in a mural of the \u201cinvestiture\u201d of a ruler of this city. While providing terminology for parts of the body, animals, and economic functions, the names of specific people are largely absent from a peace treaty between this city and Ebla. A ruler of this city, Yasmah-Adad, was criticized by his father as a beardless child for not devoting enough time to governance. This city declined in importance after (*) Hammurabi conquered it\u00a0 in 1761 BCE. For 10 points, identify this ancient city in eastern Syria on the banks of the Euphrates, most famously ruled by Zimri-Lim.", "answer": "Mari", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A style of ceramic glaze sometimes known in the West as \u201cegg and spinach\u201d was first introduced to the Middle East during this dynasty. This dynasty\u2019s victory at the Battle of Irtysh River featured members of a non-Japanese Ashina tribe on both sides. Bilge Khan\u2019s Orkhon inscription decries the recruitment of Turkic officers into this dynasty\u2019s military after it defeated the Eastern Turkic Khanate. Karashar, Kucha, Hotan, and Kashgar were the Four Garrison cities this dynasty established in the \u0100nx\u012b Protectorate. Much of this dynasty\u2019s western holdings were lost with the expansion of the (*) Tibetan Empire. This dynasty fought the short-lived Y\u0101n Dynasty, which had begun after a rebellion by a Turkish-Sogdian general. For 10 points, name this dynasty that faced the \u0100n L\u00f9sh\u0101n Rebellion.", "answer": "T\u00e1ng Dynasty", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}